Guide to the Harriett Taylor papers, 1952-1997 MS2289
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Harriett Taylor papers
1952-1997
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Taylor, Harriett R.
MS2289
9 Linear Feet 14 document boxes, 2 flat boxes
The Honorable Harriett Rosen Taylor (1932-1997) was a Senior Judge of the District of Columbia Superior Court. After graduating from Columbia Law School, she practiced labor law in the office of prominent labor and civil rights lawyers Joseph Rauh and John Silard in Washington, D.C., before becoming the District's first administrative law judge in 1976. This collection contains legal documents, notes, correspondence, note cards, clippings, awards, and photographs documenting Harriett Taylor's legal and political work from 1952 to 1997. This includes case files from Taylor's work as a labor lawyer, as well as index card files of Taylor's orders and opinions as a judge of the District of Columbia Superior Court in the 1980s.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains legal documents, notes, correspondence, note cards, clippings, awards, and photographs documenting Harriett Taylor's legal and political work from 1952 to 1997. This includes case files from Taylor's work as a labor lawyer with the law firm of Rauh and Silard in the 1960s, as well as index card files of Taylor's orders and opinions as a judge of the District of Columbia Superior Court in the 1980s. In addition, the collection contains correspondence and clippings from Taylor's Democratic National Committee campaign, as well as manuscripts, obituaries, photographs, personal correspondence, awards, certificates, and a memorial book.
Biographical / Historical
The Honorable Harriett Rosen Taylor (1932-1997) was a Senior Judge of the District of Columbia Superior Court remembered most notably for decisions that benefited poor and homeless residents of the District.
Taylor graduated from Brooklyn College and Columbia University Law School. She practiced labor law in the office of prominent labor and civil rights lawyers Joseph Rauh and John Silard in Washington, D.C., before becoming the District's first administrative law judge in 1976, working in the newly formed Office of Consumer Protection. President Jimmy Carter named her to a 15-year term on the Superior Court bench in 1979, to which she was reappointed in 1994.
In 1975, Taylor ran a campaign for Democratic National Committee member from the District of Columbia, but was unsuccessful in the bid. As a judge, she achieved prominence for two decisions in particular: in 1982, ordering Mayor Marion Barry to provide heat and hot water in four city housing projects; and in 1989, ordering improvements and expansions in District homeless shelters.
Judge Taylor was married to civil rights attorney William L. Taylor, whose papers are also held by the Special Collections Research Center.
Arrangement
Collection: Organized into five series: Litigation, Politics and personal history, Photographs, Correspondence, and D.C. Superior Court.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the family of Harriett Taylor, 2011 [2011.002]
Washington (D.C.) Politics and government; Labor unions; Law; Taylor, Harriett R.
- Litigation, 1955-1968; Series 1; 2.5 Linear Feet 6 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains briefs, notes, legal documents, correspondence, and note cards documenting Harriett Taylor's legal work, primarily as a labor lawyer with the law firm of Rauh and Silard. The material dates from 1955 to 1968.
  - Acme Industrial -- Supreme Court, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admission to NYC Bar Association, 1955; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Aero Corporation, 1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allis Chalmers working file, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Metal Products Co. v. UAW, 1962; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Bangor and Aroostook Railroad v. Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bata Shoe Co. v. United Shoe Workers of America, 1968; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen fact sheet, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, 1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, 1968; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen -- S.J. Res. 81, 1967; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen -- S.J. Res. 81, 1967; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Briefs from Taylor cases, 1964-1967; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campaign Finance (UAW Program for Clean Federal Elections; Press Release), 1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Campaign finance, 1962; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Campbell Associates, Inc. v. D.C. Armory Board, 1965; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Card files summarizing cases, 1955-1968; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Cases, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cross Company v. UAW, 1963; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Domestic Violence Plan, 1995-1996; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ex-Cell-O brief to board, 1967 June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ex-Cell-O statistics, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ex-Cell-O supplemental brief to board, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fafnir Bearing Company v. NLRB, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fafnir working file, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - GM v. UAW, 1961-1962; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Golay Answering Brief, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Golay Argument, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hoosier Cardinal -- Sup. Ct., 1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Honda working file, 1967 June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Honda, 1968; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Independent Metal Workers Union, 1963; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Kohler Company v. NLRB, 1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kohler Company v. NLRB, 1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Kohler contempt action, 1965; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - McCarthy [Sen. Eugene] v. FCC, 1968; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National Council on Agricultural Life and Labor, 1967; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Naples v. United States, 1968; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Neighbors Inc. -- ABC Board hearing, 1967 November 29; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pacific Maritime, 1968; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Professional correspondence, 1965-1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Public employee relations laws, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Pullman Co. v. Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Railway Labor Act Amendments, 1934; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Rauh and Reuther speeches, 1963-1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rauh -- memos, 1963-1967; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Reid v. McDonnell Douglas Corporation, 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rule XXII -- 88th Congress, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Scofield v. NLRB, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - United Auto Workers working files, 1962-1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - United Auto Workers v. National Labor Relations Board, 1966; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - United Auto Workers v. National Labor Relations Board, 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - United Auto Workers v. Preston Products Co., 1964; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - United Mine Workers v. Pennington, 1965; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - United Transport Service Employees and BRAC, 1968 March; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Willimart Services, Inc., 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Wisconsin Motors, 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Politics and personal history, 1952-1997; Series 2; 3.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes, 2 flat boxes
  This series contains correspondence, clippings, and other documents relating to Harriett Taylor's political work, as well as manuscripts, obituaries, other personal correspondence, awards, certificates, and a memorial book. The material dates from 1952 to 1997.
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1974; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Audiocassettes, Series 2 (Box 17)
  - Campaign -- Democratic National Committee, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Citizens' Committee for an Open Party, 1976; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Clippings including obituaries, 1974-1997; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Continuing legal education -- Litigation and Women Lawyers, 1993; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1997; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - DC Bar Association, 1967; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Framed awards and certificates, Series 2 (Box 9)
  - Framed awards and certificates, Series 2 (Box 10)
  - Gender Fairness in Judicial Education conference, 1995; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts, 1952-1955; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - March on Boston/ADA, 1975 May 17; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Memorial book: "In Memorium Harriett R. Taylor", 1997; Series 2 (Box 8)
  - Memorial monument, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Mississippi presidential election, 1968; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Personal correspondence, 1966-1968; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Political lists, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Political lists, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Deborah Rhodes' gender class, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Stanford Law School, 1996; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Taylor personnel documents, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ward 4, 1974; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Ward 4 maps, undated; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1955-1994; Series 3; 3 folder(s)
  This small series contains personal and professional photographs of Harriett Taylor from throughout her life, including her graduation from law school in 1955.
  Arranged as found.
  - Photographs -- Harriett Taylor, undated; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs -- Harriett Taylor, 1978; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- Harriett Taylor event, 1994; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1956-1988; Series 4; 1 Linear Feet 2 document boxes
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains correspondence to and from Harriett Taylor from 1956 to 1988, though primarily from the late 1970s. It documents her work first as a labor lawyer, and then as the District of Columbia's first administrative law judge.
  - Correspondence, 1956-1958; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1976; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1977; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1977; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1978; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1978; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1979 January-July; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1979; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1988; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- D.C. Superior Court, 1977-1996; Series 5; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
  This series contains legal documents, reports, correspondence, index cards, and biographical materials relating to Judge Harriett Taylor's tenure on the Washington D.C. Superior Court. Legal documents and reports primarily concern the Atchison v. Barry and Fountain v. Barry cases, which were brought to improve conditions in shelters for D.C.'s homeless population. Index card files list Judge Taylor's orders and opinions on the D.C. Superior Court. The material dates from 1977 to 1996.
  - Atchison et al. v. Barry et al., 1989; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Atchison et al. v. Barry et al., 1989-1991; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Atchison et al. v. Barry et al., 1989-1991; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Atchison et al. v. Barry et al. -- Fairness Hearing, 1989; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Atchison et al. v. Barry et al. -- Findings of Fact, 1989; Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Biography, undated; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1977; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - DC Superior Court investiture, 1979; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Fountain et al. v. Barry et al., Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Judicial evaluations, 1993; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Judicial training, 1992; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Homeless case clippings, 1989-1996; Series 5 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - HRT's Orders and Opinions (card file), 1979-1983; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Law Day, 1979; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Letters of congratulations, 1976; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Letters of congratulations, 1979; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Letters of support for DC Superior Court [1 of 2], 1978-1979; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Letters of support for DC Superior Court [2 of 2], 1978-1979; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Letters -- thank you, 1979; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Reappointment, 1993; Series 5 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Reports on the homeless, 1988-1993; Series 5 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Retirement, 1996; Series 5 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Suits against H.R. Taylor, 1981-1986; Series 5 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Trial Lawyers Award, 1993; Series 5 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Trust for Affordable Housing annual reports, 1991-1992; Series 5 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Senate confirmation, 1979; Series 5 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - White House, 1979; Series 5 (Box 12, Folder 6)